PROFESSOR: OK.
Let's step through a couple of A
star examples in this video.
Here's our first example.
We have a state spacecraft.
We have for each state the heuristic
values listed here.
And we're going to do a search-tree
visualization of
the A star tree search.
The start state is S and the goal state
is G. When we start out, we just
have the root of the search tree,
which has the state S in it.
And together with the state, we will
store the f value, which consists of e
and h So for S, the g cost is 0.
No cost has been incurred yet to reach
S because that's where we start.
And the h value, that's the heuristic
that we look up in the table.
For S, we have 7, so 0
plus 7, which is 7.
An A star search will consider all nodes
in the tree that have not been
expanded yet and expand the one
that has the lowest f cost.
There's only one node in the tree.
So that's the one with
the lowest f cost.
We expand it.
The successors for S are A and
B. We have a partial plan SA.
And we have an f cost which consists of
g plus h, which is equal to-- for
g, we look up the g cost in the previous
node, which is 0, and add the
cost of making this last transition
from S to A, which is 1.
And then for h, we look up
in the table here, 6.
Second successor of S is B. The
f cost consists of g and h.
For g, we look up at the parent
node what the g cost was for.
Then we add the cost for making
that last transition here, S
to B, which is 4.
And then for the heuristic value, we
look up the heuristic in the table for
B, which is 2.
So we have a node with f cost of
7 and a node with f cost of 6.
6 is the lowest so that's the next one
A star consider for expansion.
When we expand B, B has only one
successor, C. So we'll get one child
node here, SBC, with f consisting
of g and h.
And to find g, we look at the parent
node for the g cost to reach the
parent, which is 4.
And then we add the cost for the last
transition B to C, which is 2.
And then for the h cost, we look up in
the heuristic table heuristic for C
which is 1.
So we end up with 7 total.
A star search will look at the nodes
that haven't been expanded yet.
There are two of them, SA and SBC.
Both of them have an f cost of 7.
We're doing alphabetical tie-breaking.
SA comes alphabetically before SBC.
So we expand SA first.
A has three successors.
And go to B, to C, and to G. For go to
B, we have a partial plan SAB with an
f cost, which consists of g and h.
For g, again, we take the parent's
g cost which is 1.
We add on the cost for this last
transition from A to B, which is 2.
The heuristic value is the one
for B, which is also 2.
So we end up with an f cost of 5.
The second successor for
A is C. So we have SAC.
F cost consists of g and h.
g consists of the parent's g cost, which
is 1, plus the g costs for the
transition AC, which is 5.
And then the heuristic value, we
look up in the table the entry
for C, which is 1.
So we end up with 7.
And for the third successor of
A, which is G, we have SAG.
f again consists of g and h.
For g, we look up the parent g cost and
add the transition costs for the
last transition that we just
added, A to G, which is 12.
And the heuristic value we look up
in the table for G here is 0.
So this one has an f cost of 13.
A star proceeds by looking at all the
nodes that have not been expanded yet
and first considering the one with the
lowest f cost, which is SAB over here.
Note that-- and this is really
important-- that at this point,
amongst the nodes we have not expanded
yet, there are four of those.
There is SAB, SAC, SAG, and SBC.
One of them, namely SAG,
ends in the goal state.
It's important to keep in mind that
it's not just because we reach the
goal here that we're done.
We have to wait till we expand.
We are expanding a node that reaches
the goal state to declare success.
So at this point, we are expanding again
the one with the lowest f cost,
which is SAB.
Expanding that one, how many successors
that B had, B has one
successor C. So we're going
to end up with SABC.
The f cost for this node
consists of g and h.
g, we look up the parent's g cost, 3.
We add the cost for the transition
B to C, which is 2.
And for h, we look up the heuristic
value for C, which is 1.
And we end up with a total of 6.
6 is the lowest f cost of all nodes
that have not been expanded yet.
So we're expanding SABC next.
C has just one successor, G. So we end
up with SABCG and f costs, which
consist of g and h, where for g, we have
to look up the parent's g cost,
which is 5.
Add the cost of the last transition
C to G, which is 3.
And then add the heuristic value of
the last node G, which is the
heuristic value of 0.
We end up with 8.
We do alphabetical tie-breaking,
making a start with SAC.
C has one successor, G. So
we end up with SACG.
The f cost is consisting of g plus h.
g consists of the parent's g cost, which
is 6, plus the transition C to
G's cost, which is 3.
And then the heuristic at
the goal state is 0.
So we end up with 9.
SBC is the node that has not been
expanded yet with the lowest f cost.
So we expand that one next.
C has only one successor, G.
So we end up with SBCG.
It has an f cost that
consists of g and h.
For g, we look up the g cost
of the parent, which is 6.
We add the cost of the CG
transition, which is 3.
And then we have to add the heuristic
value which is 0 here.
So we end up with 9.
Of the nodes currently in consideration
for expansion, we have
one of cost 8, one of cost 9, one
of cost 13, one of cost 9.
8 is the lowest.
So we'll expand this one next.
This one ends in the goal state.
And when we are about to expand a node
that ends in the goal state, that
means we're done and we're return that
node as our solution to the problem.
So in this case, our
solution is SABCG.
And the cost of that path is 8.
Is SABCG optimal?
Well, for A star research, we have the
guarantee that it will return the
optimal solution.
So it is optimal if the heuristic
h is admissible.
To find out whether h is admissible, we
need to look at all these entries
here and verify that they are indeed
underestimates of the shortest path to
a goal state from those states.
Not going to step through that here,
but indeed, it can be verified that
each of these are underestimates of
the cheapest path to a goal state.
So we have that indeed,
SABCG is optimal.
Now, let's run A star research again.
But visualize our process with a
priority queue rather than a
search-tree.
Same problem as before.
Our priority queue will start with just
one entry, S. And the f cost for
S is 0 for the g cost plus
7 for the heuristic.
A star research will look at the
priority queue, pop the node with the
highest priority.
There's only one.
So that that one node is the one
that's going to be popped.
And put all its successors
into the priority queue.
S has two successor states, A
and B, so we get SA and SB.
And for the f cost associated
with them, we have the g
cost plus an h cost.
And the g cost is the cost of the parent
node, S plus the cost of the
transition SA, which is 1.
The heuristic is the heuristic
for A, which is 6.
And for SB, we also have a g cost of 0
plus now the cost from S to B, which
is 4, plus the heuristic value
for B, which is 2.
Next, A star research will pop the one
with the highest priority as it always
does, which is the one with the lowest
f cost, which is SB, with
an f cost of 6.
SA stays in the queue.
B has one successor, C.
So we end up with SBC.
The g cost is the g cost of its parent
node, 4 plus the cost for the
transition from B to C, which is 2.
And the heuristic value for C is 1.
Popping the one with the lowest f cost,
in this case, there's a tie.
Alphabetical tie-breaking makes
us pick SA before SBC.
A has three successors, leading us
to the following priority queue.
The g cost for SAB is 1 from the
parent node plus 2 for the AB
transition.
And then adding h, which is 2 for B, the
second successor of AC with SAC,
the f cost consisting of g plus h, we
have for g 1 from the parent plus 5
for the transition.
And for h, we have 1.
And then the third successor phase G,
and here we end up with a g cost also
of 1 from the parent, plus 12
for the transition now,
plus 0 for the heuristic.
And then we still have SBC
on the priority queue.
So I'll put it down here, SBC, with a
g cost of 6 and a heuristic of 1.
Now, the lowest cost is 5,
which is found over here.
We pop SAB from the priority queue.
B has one successor, C. The g cost is
3 from the parent plus 2 from the
transition.
The heuristic value for C is 1.
And then we retain all the other ones.
Now, the node with the lowest f cost,
SABC with an f cost of 6,
we expand that one.
C as one successor, G. So
we end up with SABCG.
G contribution is 5 from the parent
plus 3 from the CG transition.
Then the heuristic value of G is 0.
And we retain the other three.
Now, with the lowest f cost is a tie.
There is SAC with 7 and
there is SBC with 7.
Alphabetical tie-breaking
makes us pick SAC first.
SAC has one successor, G. C has one
successor, G. So we end up expanding
that into just one node, SACG.
The g cost comes from the parent,
6 plus transition CG 3.
And the heuristic at G is 0.
And the other ones we just retain
on the priority queue.
Now, the one with the lowest f cost
is SBC with an f cost of 7.
C is one successor, G. We end up with
putting one new node, SBCG.
The g cost consists of 6 from the parent
plus 3 from the transition CG.
And the heuristic value of G is 0.
And we copy the other three over.
Now, the one with the lowest f cost
is SABCG, has an f cost of 8.
We're about to expand this one, but we
notice that it ends in the goal state.
That means we are done.
We declare success.
We have SABCG as a solution
found by A star research.
We discussed in the previous slide
why this is the optimal solution.
Now, let's move on to graph search.
As a reminder, what's the difference
between tree search and graph search?
In graph search, when you are about to
expand a node, you check whether you
ever expanded a node that ends in the
same state as the node you're
currently about expand.
If that's the case, you don't
expand the current node.
You just take it out of
the priority queue.
And that's it.
So you avoid reexpanding plans that
lead into the same state.
I'm actually going to do a search
tree visualization.
But the search tree is perhaps
a slightly more interesting
visualization to look at.
So let's start with the root.
We just have S with an f cost of 0, plus
the heuristic at f, which is 7.
We start graph search.
We'll look at the nodes currently
available for expansion.
So that's just S.
S has two successors, A and B. We
expand SA, which has an f cost
consisting of g plus h where g consists
of the g cost of the parent,
which is 0, plus the cost of
the transition, which is 1.
And then the heuristic
value for A is 6.
And for B, we have a g cost from the
parent of 0, plus a cost for the SB
transition of 4, plus a
heuristic value of 2.
We have expanded S. And so in A star
graph search, what we do, we have a
separate thing called a Closed List.
This keeps track of states we
have expanded in the past.
And this Closed List now contains S.
SB has the lowest f cost, f cost of 6.
So we expand B. B has one successor,
C. So we end up with SBC.
g cost of 4 from the parent, plus 2 from
the transition, and an h cost for
C of 1-- we have expanded the state B.
So it goes into our Closed List.
Both nodes have an equal f cost of 7.
Alphabetical tie-breaking makes us
pick SA first for expansion.
A has three successors.
We have SAB.
We have SAC.
And we have SAG.
The f cost for SAB consists of g, which
is 1 from the parent, plus 2 for
the transition, plus 2 from the
heuristic value for B. For SAC, we
have an f cost that consists of g cost,
which has 1 from the parent,
plus 5 from the transition, and then
the heuristic value for C is 1.
And for the last one here, SAG, we have
g cost, which has a contribution
of 1 from the parent, 12 from the
AG transition, and then a
heuristic value of 0.
At this point, we've expanded A.
A goes onto our Closed List.
Now, let's look at which one
has the lowest f cost.
We have 5 here which
is the lowest, SAB.
So we're considering
SAB for expansion.
It turns out, however, B has
already been expanded.
It's in our Closed List.
So we don't expand this one.
We're done with that range.
Which one is next?
In terms of f cost, we have SAC
with 7 and we have SBC with 7.
We'll do alphabetical tie-breaking.
So SAC will get expanded.
C has one successor, G. We have one
child here, SACG with an f cost
consisting of g and h. g consists of the
g cost of the parent, which is 6,
plus the cost of the transition which is
3, and then the heuristic value of
G is 0, for a total of 9.
Completes the expansion of this node
with the [INAUDIBLE] at C. So C goes
onto our Closed List.
Looking at our nodes, we have 9 here,
we have 13 here, and 7 here.
7 is next.
So we consider SBC for expansion next.
The last state here, C, is, however,
in our Closed List, which means we
don't expand.
We just stop this branch
in the search tree.
And we move on to the next one.
And the next lowest one
here is SACG with 9.
We consider this one for expansion.
We notice that it reaches
the goal state.
So we declare success.
We've found a path to the goal, SACG.
And it has a cost of 9.
Is this optimal?
Well, we saw before that there's
a path that's cheaper than 9.
In fact, the path that we found before
running A star research was one that
ran from S to A, to B, to C, and to
G for a total cost of 8, which
is less than 9.
So what happened here?
We ran an A star graph search and we
ended up with a solution that has a
cost of 9, which is not optimal.
What happened here is that we are
using a heuristic that is not
consistent.
And because the heuristic is not
consistent, we are not guaranteed that
A star graph search will
find the optimal path.
Indeed, the optimal path, which we know
is SABCG, did not get explored.
Because when we were going down the
search tree in the direction that
would lead to that path which is over
here, we decided not to expand SAB
because B was already
in the Closed List.
How did that happen?
Well, because the heuristic is not
consistent, it happened to be the case
that we already expanded B in a
different part of the search tree.
And when we expanded B in a different
part of the search tree, we had
reached B in a more expensive way.
And so this cheaper way of reaching
B through A was not explored.
So where is that inconsistency
in the heuristic?
Let's write down the condition
for h to be consistent.
Condition is that for all S and S prime
where we can go from S to S
prime, it needs to be the case that hs
minus hs prime is more than or equal
to the cost to go from S to S prime.
Now, let's see if we can find the
violation in our problem here.
Yes!
Found it.
Let S be A and S prime be B. Then we
have the condition ha minus hb should
be smaller than or equal to 2.
ha is 6. hb is 2.
We have now 6 minus 2 is 4.
It should be smaller than 2,
which is not the case.
So we have a violation of our
consistency condition.
And that's why we don't have the
guarantee here that A star graph
search would find an optimal path.
Let's move on.
Let's again use the search tree
visualization because it's a little
more compact and conveys a
little more information.
And we have now updated our heuristic
h to be consistent.
You can verify that the consistency
condition is satisfied for these
heuristic values.
Let's run our A star
graph search again.
We start with S with an f cost
consisting of g and h.
g is 0.
h, we read off from the table as 7.
We expand S, which puts
S on our Closed List.
S has two successors, A
and B. So we have SA.
The f cost for SA is the g cost of the
parent, which is 0, plus the costs for
transition SA, which is 1, plus the cost
from the heuristic value at A,
which is 6.
And we have for SB a g cost of 0, plus
4, plus the heuristic value of 4.
We have expanded S, which is
in our Closed List now.
Who's up next for expansion?
7 versus 8, 7 is a lower f cost.
So we'll expand SA, which will
put A on our Closed List.
A has three successors, B, C, and G.
So we're going to have SAB with an
f cost consisting of g and h.
g is 1 from the parent, plus 2 from
the transition, plus the heuristic
value at B, which is 4.
Then for SAC, we have an f cost of 1
from the g cost of the parent plus 5
from the transition AC.
And then we add the heuristic
value at C, which is 2.
And then lastly, we have SAG, which
has an f cost consisting of
a g and an h cost.
The g has 1 from the parent.
And we add 12 for the AG transition.
And the heuristic value at G is 0.
So now, we have a 7 here, 8 here,
13 here, and 8 over here.
7 is the lowest.
So we'll expand SAB first.
So we expand B. B has one successor,
C. We have SABC.
The g cost is 3 from the parent
plus 2 from the transition.
The h cost is 2.
We have expanded B so we put
it on the Closed List.
Now again, the lowest f cost
is down this branch.
We expand SABC.
C has one successor G. So
we end up with SABCG.
The f cost consists of a
g cost and an h cost.
The g cost is 5 from the parent, plus
3 from the transition, and then plus
an h cost of 0 at the goal
state for a total of 8.
We put C on our Closed List.
Now, the next one with the lowest f
value, there's the three-way tie.
There is SABCG, there is
SAC, and there is SB.
SABCG comes alphabetically first.
So that's one we'll expand first.
This one ends in the goal state.
That means we're done.
We declare success.
And we return SABCG as our solution.
[COMPUTER BELL RINGS]
And it has a cost of 8.
This is the optimal path.
We're guaranteed this is the case
because the heuristic we have here is
a consistent heuristic.
An A star graph search is guaranteed to
return an optimal solution when you
have a consistent heuristic.
OK.
That's it for our A star
search examples.